A Guide to the Michael Collins Papers, 1907-2004
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Michael Collins Papers, 1907-2004
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1989-029
24.9 cu. ft. 39 boxes; 1 folder; 1 model
The collection includes the papers of Michael Collins--pilot, astronaut, assistant secretary of state, director of the National Air and Space Museum and author, dating from 1907-2004. Materials include reports, instruction manuals, personal notes, printed materials, audio recordings, photographs, awards and memorabilia associated with Collins' Air Force, NASA, State Department and NASM careers. There are also papers and research relating to Collins' writings; materials from public speaking engagements and board and club memberships; and small sets of personal correspondence and biographical material.
Collins, Michael, 1930-
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Michael Collins Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1989. Additional donations were acquired in 2005 and 2007.
Biographical/Historical Information
Michael Collins--pilot, astronaut, U.S. assistant secretary of state, National Air and Space Museum director, and author--was born in Rome, Italy on October 31, 1930. He graduated from Saint Albans School in Washington, D.C. before attending the U.S. Military Academy (West Point), where he obtained a bachelor of science degree in 1952.
Collins received an Air Force commission and, after pilot training, was assigned to Nellis Air Base for advanced training on the F-86 Sabrejet. Upon completion of training, he was assigned to the 21st Fighter- Bomber Wing, stationed in Victorville, California and, later, France. In 1961, Collins completed test pilot school and was assigned to Edwards Air Force Base, where he tested experimental fighter jets. (In the meantime, he had married Patricia Finnegan; the couple would have three children: Kathleen, Ann and Michael.)
Interested in NASA's manned space program, Collins enrolled in the newly established Aerospace Pilot School in 1963. In October of that year, he was among the third group of astronauts selected by NASA. Collins served as a member of the backup crew for the Gemini 7 mission and as pilot of NASA's Gemini 10 mission (launched July 18, 1966) with commander John Young. Among the mission's noteworthy accomplishments were the establishment of a new orbital altitude record, a rendezvous with an Agena target vehicle, and two spacewalks conducted by Collins.
Due to the rotational basis on which astronauts were assigned to Apollo missions, Collins was originally scheduled to be a member of the Apollo 8 flight crew. His need for back surgery, however, forced his re- assignment to a later mission. The postponement placed Collins on the crew of Apollo 11 (launched July 16, 1969), the first manned mission to land on the lunar surface. As the mission's command module pilot, Collins orbited the moon while commander Neil Armstrong and lunar module pilot Edwin E. "Buzz" Aldrin descended to its surface.
In January 1970, Collins resigned from NASA and served as assistant secretary of state for public affairs before becoming the first director of the Smithsonian Institution's National Air and Space Museum in April 1971; he was promoted to undersecretary of the Smithsonian in April 1978. During this time, Collins began writing about his experiences in the space program, leading to his book Carrying the Fire(and a subsequent children's adaptation, Flying to the Moon and Other Strange Places). His expertise and talents led to numerous requests for speaking engagements, articles and book reviews. In 1988, he published Liftoff!, a book on the history and future of space exploration; his Mission to Mars was published in 1990.
Collins served on the boards of numerous organizations and corporations throughout the 1970s and 1980s. He became vice-president of field operations for the Vought Corporation in 1980, then resigned to head his own consulting firm, Michael Collins Associates, in 1985. He retired from the Air Force Reserve with the rank of major general in 1982.
Collins' awards include the Presidential Medal of Freedom; the Collier, Harmon and Goddard trophies; the Air Force Distinguished Service Medal with Oak Leaf Cluster; the Distinguished Flying Cross and many others. He has received awards from eleven other countries and honorary degrees from six colleges and universities.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Michael Collins--pilot, astronaut, assistant secretary of state, director of the National Air and Space Museum (NASM), and author--include items (printed material, notes, correspondence, photos, and audio recordings) from Collins' Air Force career, training at the U. S. Test Pilot School and Experimental Flight Center, participation in NASA's Gemini and Apollo programs, and tenure at the State Department and NASM. The collection also includes materials associated with three of Collins' books (Carrying the Fire, Flying to the Moon and Other Strange Places, and Liftoff!), as well as various articles and book reviews written by him. Collins' many public appearances are represented here with background materials, speech notes, texts, printed material and photos. The collection also includes a number of files, largely composed of correspondence, devoted to Collins' involvement with various boards and clubs. In addition, there are small sets of personal correspondence and biographical materials. An assortment of honors and memorabilia completes the collection.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series:
SERIES I. Air Force, 1953-1973. This series contains Collins' individual flight record (including his later NASA flights) and an accident report for the crash of an F-86 fighter jet piloted by him. The series also contains a number of test pilot manuals from the USAF Flight Test Center and reports written by Collins while at the Experimental Flight Test Pilot School. Also included are a few items relating to survival training and an Aerospace Research Pilot School publication containing sketches and photos of ARPS and Experimental Test Pilot School graduates. The series is arranged chronologically.
SERIES II. Project Gemini, 1962-1967. The Project Gemini Series contains a number of preparatory materials which include instruction manuals, class materials and Collins' own notes on astronomy, geology and the Gemini spacecraft. From the Gemini 10 flight, the series contains an audio recording of the liftoff, transcripts of voice communications and mission commentaries, and photographs. The series also includes official post- mission reports and two Gemini 10 newsclipping scrapbooks. The series is arranged in subseries by material type.
SERIES III. Project Apollo, 1966-2004. Like the Project Gemini series, this series contains Collins' preparatory notes. It also contains transcripts of mission commentary, flight communications, and press feeds during post- flight recovery of the command module. The series includes a number of audio recordings, which range from a pre-flight press conference to television coverage of the mission, and post-mission public appearances by the crew. Print media coverage of the mission may be found in a set of NASA Current News publications and other printed materials. The series contains approximately 200 mission photos and a number of commemorative materials. (Among the more unusual items are a collection of songs and poems inspired by Apollo 11 and a book of congratulatory letters from French civic leaders.) Post-mission materials include files devoted to five- and ten-year anniversary observances of the moon landing and audio recordings relating to the Apollo program and missions 12 and 13. The series is arranged in subseries by material type. Within subseries, materials are in chronological order wherever possible.
SERIES IV. Assistant Secretary of State, 1969-1971. Collins' brief career with the U. S. State Department is chronicled here through notes, correspondence (including letters from President Nixon), audio recordings and printed materials. The series is arranged by item format, then chronologically.
SERIES V. National Air and Space Museum, 1971-1979. This series contains materials relating to Collins' directorship of NASM--particularly to the museum's design, groundbreaking and opening. The collection also includes newsclippings devoted to museum exhibits and Collins as director. Audio recordings of events commemorating Collins' farewell complete the series. Arranged by form of item, then chronologically.
SERIES VI. Boards and Clubs, 1973-1989. This series, largely devoted to the many advisory and editorial boards on which Collins served throughout the 1970s and 1980s, contains correspondence, notes, printed materials and photos. The series also includes a few folders on clubs to which Collins belonged. The series is arranged alphabetically by organization name.
SERIES VII. Writings, 1908-2004. This series contains materials relating to the writing and publication of Collins' books Carrying the Fire; Flying to the Moon and Other Strange Places; and Liftoff! and includes background materials, typescripts, galley proofs, reviews and publicity. (The files for Carrying the Fire also contain correspondence with Charles Lindbergh about his foreword to the book.) A number of Collins' articles, book reviews and opinion / editorial pieces are included here as well. The series is arranged in subseries by publication type (book, magazine article, book review, etc.), then chronologically within each subseries.
SERIES VIII. Speeches, 1970-1996. Collins' many public addresses throughout the 1970s and 1980s are represented here with background materials, speech texts, printed materials and photographs. The series is arranged chronologically by date of speech.
SERIES IX. Personal Correspondence, 1963-1973. This small series consists of correspondence which did not fit neatly into those series devoted to specific aspects of Collins' career. It includes a number of letters relating to NASA and the Apollo program. (Most noteworthy are letters from "Buzz" Aldrin, Charles Lindbergh and Lyndon B. Johnson.) The series is arranged chronologically.
SERIES X. Biographical Materials, 1966-2003. Like the personal correspondence series, this series was created from materials not associated with any specific aspect of Collins' public career. The series includes a few printed materials containing interviews or biographical sketches of Collins and several photographs. The series is arranged chronologically.
SERIES XI. Honors and Memorabilia, 1961-1989. This series contains awards--in the form of certificates, medals and plaques from the United States, individual states, foreign countries, military organizations, and private corporations--honoring Collins and his work. The series contains just a few items of memorabilia, among which are a piece of fabric from the Kitty Hawk "Wright Flyer," Collins' pilot clipboard, a Gemini sunscreen plate, a short film of Collins family scenes and commemorative items from NASA's Apollo and Voyager missions.
Separated Materials
The following items were transferred to the Rare Book Collection:
Aeronautics: The American Magazine of Aerial Locomotion, 8(5), November 1910.
Hallion, Richard P., "Girding for War: Perspectives on Research, Development, Acquisition, and the Decision-making Environment of the 1980's." (Edwards Air Force Base, CA: History Office, Air Force Flight Test Center, 1985).
Journey to Halley's Comet([S.l.]: NASA, 1980).
National Security Strategy of the United States(Washington, D.C.: The White House, 1988).
Origin and Evolution of Life--Implications for the Planets: a Scientific Strategy for the 1980's(Washington, D. C.: National Academy of Sciences, 1981).
Our First Quarter Century of Achievement... Just the Beginning[NASA 25th anniversary press kit] ([S.l.]: NASA, 1983).
Report to the President: Actions to Implement the Recommendations of the Presidential Commission on the Space Shuttle Challenger Accident[Washington, D.C.: U.S.G.P.O., 1986].
To the Moon: the Story in Sound[sound recordings with accompanying book] (New York: Time Life Records, 1969).
Index Terms
Persons:
Collins, Michael, 1930-
Corporate Names:
Project Apollo (U.S.).; Project Gemini (U.S.).; United States. National Aeronautical and Space Administration.
Occupations:
Astronauts; Authors; Businesspeople
Subjects:
Archives of American Aerospace Exploration (AAAE); Science and Technology
Contents List
- SERIES I. AIR FORCE, 1953-1973
  - Individual flight record, 1953-1973 (Box-folder 1-1 (2 folders))
    Scope and Contents note
    (includes NASA flights)
  - Major accident report: F-86F - Chaumont Air Base (France) August 16 1956 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - "Aerodynamics Handbook for Performance Flight Testing" (Air Force Flight Test Center) - vol. 1, July 1960 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - "Pilot's Handbook for Performance Flight Testing" (Air Force Flight Test Center), September 1 1960 (Box-folder 1-4 (2 folders))
  - "Combined Performance Report" by Michael Collins (USAF Experimental Flight Test Pilot School), December 1960 (Box-folder 1-5 (2 folders))
  - "A Limited Stability and Control Investigation of the T-28A, T-33A, B-57E, and F-86E; a Qualitative Evaluation of the T-28A and F-104D and Spin Tests on the T-28A and F-86F" by Michael Collins (USAF Experimental Flight Test Pilot School), April 10 1961 (Box-folder 2-1 (3 folders))
  - "Pilot's Handbook for Stability and Control Flight Testing" (Air Force Flight Test Center)
    - vol. 1, May 1961 (Box-folder 2-2)
    - vol. 2, March 1961 (Box-folder 2-3)
  - "Flight Qualification of Fletcher and Royal Jet F-104 200-Gallon Nestable Pylon Tanks" by Frank N. Lucero and Michael Collins, February 1962 (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Air Force survival training, c.1964 (Box-folder 2-5)
  - The USAF Aerospace Research Pilot School, 1967 (Box-folder 2-6)
    (publication containing sketches and photos of graduates from ARPS and the USAF Experimental Flight Test Pilot School from 1955 to 1967)
- SERIES II. PROJECT GEMINI, 1962-1967
  - Gemini (I-IX)
    - "Introductory Notes on Astronomy" by John H. Craigie, August 1962 (Box-folder 3-1)
    - Gemini training notebook, 1963-1964, n.d. (Box-folder 3-2)
    - Aeromedical Evaluation for Space Pilots, July 1963 (Box-folder 3-3)
    - "Schedule and Outline of Courses in Geology: Astronaut Training Program," January 8 1964 (Box-folder 3-4 (2 folders))
    - "Gemini - Titan II Air Force Launch Vehicle Press Handbook" (2nd Edition), c.1965 (Box-folder 3-5 (2 folders))
    - "Gemini Program Flight Summary Report (Missions I-VII)," July 1966 (Box-folder 4-1)
    - "Summary of Gemini Extravehicular Activity," June 1967 (Box-folder 5-7 (2 folders))
  - Gemini X
    - Gemini 10 notebook, 1966 (Box-folder 3-6)
    - "Final Gemini X Flight Plan," June 22 1966 (Box-folder 3-7 (2 folders))
    - "Gemini Operations Handbook - Spacecraft 10 (Revision A): Section II - Controls and Displays," July 1 1966 (Box-folder 4-2 (3 folders))
    - "Gemini 10 Mission Highlights," [July 1966] (Box-folder 4-3)
    - "Gemini X Voice Communications (Air-to-Ground, Ground-to-Air and On-board Transcriptions)," July 18-21 1966 (Box-folder 4-5 (2 folders))
    - "Gemini-X Mission Data: Air to Ground Voice Transcripts (Preliminary)"
      - 00:00:00 - 6:67:48, July 18 1966 (Box-folder 4-6)
      - 07:16:47 - 23:13:26, July 18-19 1966 (Box-folder 4-7)
      - 23:13:26 - 70:46:39 [pt. 1], July 19-21 1966 (Box-folder 5-1)
      - 23:13:26 - 70:46:39 [pt. 2], July 19-21 1966 (Box-folder 5-2)
    - "Gemini 10 Mission Commentary," July 19 1966 (Box-folder 5-3)
    - "Gemini X Technical Debriefing," July 26 1966 (Box-folder 5-4 (2 folders))
    - "Gemini Program Mission Report: Gemini X," August 1966 (Box-folder 5-5 (3 folders))
    - "Interim Report: Manned Spaceflight Experiments - Gemini X Mission," March 1967 (Box-folder 5-6)
    - Gemini 10 rendezvous with Agena target vehicle photo, July 1966 (Box-folder 34-1)
    - Gemini model (item on display in Special Collection)
  - A/V and Photographic Materials
    - Gemini X liftoff commentary [reel-to-reel audio recording], July 18 1966, [2 copies] (Box-folder 4-4)
    - NASA photographs (black and white), 1966, n.d. (Box-folder 6-1 (3 folders))
    - NASA photographs (color), 1965-1966, n.d. (Box-folder 6-2 (4 folders))
      [See also Oversize Materials]
    - Gemini 10 photo album, 1966, n.d. (Box-folder 7-1 (5 folders))
    - Gemini 10 scrapbook, 1966 (Box-folder 7-2)
    - "Gemini 10 - Flug: im Spiegel der deutschen Presse," 1966 (Box-folder 7-3)
      (scrapbook of German newsclippings)
- SERIES III. PROJECT APOLLO, 1966-2004
  - Press Releases/Print Media
    - "Apollo Spacecraft News Reference," [April 1969] (Box-folder 8-3 (2 folders))
    - Apollo News Center press releases, July 13-24 1969 (Box-folder 8-4)
    - Press feeds from WUI press center aboard USS Hornet during recovery of Columbia, July 24 1969 (Box-folder 11-4)
    - NASA Current News, July 16-August 8 1969
      - July 16 1969 (Box-folder 13-5)
      - July 17 1969 (Box-folder 13-6)
      - July 18 1969 (Box-folder 13-7)
      - July 22 1969 (Box-folder 13-8)
      - July 23 1969 (Box-folder 13-9)
      - July 24 1969 (Box-folder 13-10)
      - July 25 1969 (Box-folder 13-11)
      - July 28 1969 (Box-folder 13-12)
      - July 29 1969 (Box-folder 13-13)
      - July 30 1969 (Box-folder 13-14)
      - July 31 1969 (Box-folder 13-15)
      - August 1 1969 (Box-folder 13-16)
      - August 4 1969 (Box-folder 13-17)
      - August 5 1969 (Box-folder 13-18)
      - August 6 1969 (Box-folder 13-19)
      - August 7 1969 (Box-folder 14-1)
      - August 8 1969 (Box-folder 14-2)
    - NASA Current News Apollo 11 special issue, Jul-August 1969 (Box-folder 14-3 (2 folders))
    - NASA Reports and Press Releases (Box-folder 38-34)
    - NASA 10th Anniversary Special Report (Box-folder 38-35)
    - Press Releases about Astronauts
    - Materials about the Future of Spaceflight, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 35-21)
    - Other printed material, 1969-1970, n.d. (Box-folder 14-4)
      (includes copies of Politica, a Serbo-Croatian magazine)
  - A/V and Photographic Materials
    - Reel-to-reel audio recordings, July 14 1969, n.d. (Box-folder 9-1)
      - Press conference, July 14 1969
      - Thomas O. Paine
      - Collins family
    - Apollo 11 television coverage [reel-to-reel audio recording], July 1969 (Box-folder 11-2)
    - Apollo 11 lunar descent and ascent - flight director loop [reel-to-reel audio recording], July 1969, [2 copies] (Box-folder 11-3)
    - "Temporary Composite on Apollo 11" [reel-reel audio recording], [July 1969] (Box-folder 11-7)
    - "Apollo 11 Capsule" radio program [reel-to-reel audio recording], August 7 1969 (Box-folder 12-1)
    - Press conference [reel-to-reel audio recording], August 12 1969 (Box-folder 12-2)
    - Parades (Chicago and New York) [reel-to-reel audio recording], August 13 1969 (Box-folder 12-3)
    - Dinner with President Nixon [reel-to-reel audio recording], August 13 1969, [2 copies] (Box-folder 12-4)
    - Television appearances [reel-to-reel audio recordings], July 5-August 17 1969 (Box-folder 12-5)
      - "Face the Nation," August 17 1969
      - Press conference, July 5 1969
      - Houston parade, August 16 1969
    - Congressional visit [reel-to-reel audio recording, ]September 16 1969 (Box-folder 12-6)
    - Television broadcasts [reel-to-reel audio recordings], 1969 (Box-folder 13-3)
      - "Rocketry," c. 1969
      - "Apollo 11 Capsule," 1969
      - "The President's Dinner," August 13 1969
    - Radio programs commemorating one-year anniversary of moon landing [reel-to- reel audio recordings], 1970, [2 items] (Box-folder 14-8)
    - Media coverage of Apollo 12 and Apollo 13 [reel-to-reel audio recordings], c. 1969-1970, [2 items] (Box-folder 15-3)
    - Media appearances relating to the space program [reel-to-reel audio recordings], 1969-1971, n.d. (Box-folder 15-4)
      - Grumman, September 17 1969
      - von Braun (Dick Cavett Show), October28 1970
      - Hubert Humphrey on space, June 16 1970
      - Norman Mailer on Apollo 11 (Today Show), January 11 1971
      - Swigert and Apollo Program
    - NASA photos (black and white), July 1969 (Box-folder 16-1 (13 folders))
    - NASA photos (color), July 1969 (Box-folder 17-1 (9 folders))
    - Miscellaneous photos, c. 1969, (includes Collins in laboratory, life support schematic, astronauts' wives, post-mission tour, and Apollo 12) (Box-folder 17-2)
  - Apollo 11
    - Apollo training notebook, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 8-1)
    - Apollo 11 training notebook, 1969 (Box-folder 8-2)
    - Apollo 11 mission commentary transcripts, July 16-24 1969
      - July 16 1969 (Box-folder 9-2)
      - July 17 1969 (Box-folder 9-3)
      - July 18 1969 (Box-folder 9-4)
      - July 19 1969 (Box-folder 9-5)
      - July 20 1969 (Box-folder 9-6 (2 folders))
      - July 21 1969 (Box-folder 9-7)
      - July 22 1969 (Box-folder 9-8)
      - July 23 1969 (Box-folder 9-9)
      - July 24 1969 (Box-folder 9-10)
    - "Apollo 11 Technical Air-to-Ground Voice Transcription (Goss Net 1)," July 1969 (Box-folder 10-1 (6 folders))
    - "Apollo 11 Command Module Voice Dump Transcription," July 1969
      - Tapes 11-03301 to 11-03303 (Box-folder 10-2)
      - Tapes 11-03304 to 11-03307 (Box-folder 10-3)
      - Tapes 11-03309; 11-03311 to 11-03314 (Box-folder 10-4)
      - Tapes 11-03318 to 11-03320; 11-03322 (Box-folder 10-5)
      - Tapes 11-03323 to 11-03328; 11-03331 (Box-folder 10-6)
    - Apollo 11 Onboard Voice Transcription," August 1969 (Box-folder 11-1 (3 folders))
    - "Apollo 11 Technical Crew Debriefing"
      - vol. 1, July 31 1969 (Box-folder 11-5 (2 folders))
      - vol. 2, July 31 1969 (Box-folder 11-6 (2 folders))
    - "Apollo 11 Mission Report," November 1969 (Box-folder 13-2 (2 folders))
    - Publications Concerning the Lunar Landing
      - Life-To the Moon and Back Special Edition (Box-folder 39-4)
      - Life-Off to the Moon (July 4, 1969) (Box-folder 39-1)
      - Life-Leaving For the Moon (July 25, 1969) (Box-folder 39-2)
      - Life-On the Moon (August 8, 1969) (Box-folder 39-3)
      - Life-To the Moon and Back Special Edition (Box-folder 39-5)
      - Epoca-Numero Speciale a Colori Luna, c.1969 (Box-folder 39-6)
    - Correspondence
      - Congratulations following the Lunar Landing (Box-folder 38-27)
      - Correspondence in Response to the Lunar Landing (Box-folder 38-28)
      - Well Wishes for the Apollo 11 Crew (1969) (Box-folder 38-45)
    - Book of greetings signed by French civic leaders, 1969 (Box-folder 14-7)
    - Songs and poems inspired by Apollo 11
      - Printed material, 1969-1972, n.d. (Box-folder 14-5 (2 folders))
      - Recordings, 1969, n.d. (Box-folder 14-6 (2 folders))
    - Artwork Inspired by Apollo 11
      - "The Great Moment" by Paul Calle: correspondence and commemorative booklet (Box-folder 36-9)
    - "Some Photographic Results of the Apollo 11 Mission" by Paul A. Larsen, February 27 1970 (Box-folder 13-4)
    - Apollo 11 five-year anniversary
      - Apollo 11 five-year anniversary, 1974 (Box-folder 15-1)
      - Materials Concerning the Fifth Anniversary of the Lunar Landing (Box-folder 35-18)
    - Apollo 11 ten-year anniversary, 1979 (Box-folder 15-2 (2 folders))
      (includes letter from Jimmy Carter)
    - Apollo 11 10-year anniversary, 1979 (Box-folder 34-4)
      - "Men on the Moon: a 10th Anniversary Report" - LI(Newsday's Magazine for Long Island), July 15 1979
      - "A Today Tribute to Apollo 11" - Today, July 15 1979
    - Apollo 11 fifteen-year anniversary (Box-folder 35-19)
    - Apollo 11 twenty-year anniversary
      - Ad Astra- Special Issue Twentieth Anniversary of the Lunar Landing (July-August 1989)